welcome to untangling the world knot of
consciousness
wrestling with the hard problems of mind
and meaning in the modern scientific age
my name is john verviki i'm a cognitive
psychologist and cognitive scientist at
the university of toronto in canada
throughout the entire series i will be
joined in dialogue by my good friend and
colleague
greg enriquez from james madison
university in the united states
throughout we are going to wrestle with
the hard problems of how we can give an
account
of a phenomenal like consciousness
within
the scientific worldview how we can
wrestle with that problem in conjunction
with the problem that greg calls the
problem of psychology
that is pervasive throughout psychology
which is that psychology has no unified
descriptive metaphysics
by which it talks about mind and or
behavior
throughout this we will be talking about
some of the most important philosophical
cognitive scientific and neuroscientific
accounts of consciousness
so i hope you'll join us throughout uh
last time uh
greg did this excellent thing where he
took sort of the philosophical problems
given to us
uh most prominently by descartes by the
cohort of other people galileo etc
and then he showed how that just sort of
unfolded through what he has aptly named
uh the problem of psychology and so what
we have what we're seeing is
that the problem of consciousness is
enmeshed with
the problem of of our
commitment to the scientific worldview
and i neither greg nor i
are anti-scientific that's not the point
of what i just said what we're trying to
show is that
descartes uh creation of what's been
called the mind
body problem and that's what all the
arguments have shown was deeply enmeshed
uh with the creation of the scientific
worldview
and so that's one problematic on one
side and then great
and these are not independent but
following from that
uh greg showed an important
specification of that problematic
in the problem of psychology which is
the discipline that is supposed to be
at least officially studying the mind um
can't get it [ __ ] together um in the
sense of giving us a coherent
picture that we could then bring into
how you know the formulation of the
problem what's the relationship between
uh mind and matter and then greg and i
both acknowledge that that's now been
exacerbated by the
uh by the emergence of you know
additional
um competing sciences of mind like
neuroscience and artificial intelligence
uh and linguistics etc and so we have a
very
problematic situation greg i think very
difficult
amen amen and i'll just say that
when we understand the emergence of what
happened as you articulated with the
modern science
revolution it was to the create the
split between okay you have secondary
representation
oh there's a primary quantity quality
out here
right and then we have an
epistemological change in
empiricism really where it's like oh
it's empiricism is what you see it's
like wait a minute we have to factor out
what you see and measure it
from a third person perspective okay
and then if it's a third person
perspective but what we're also
interested in is also a first person
perspective
well that's a real that's an
epistemological problem right
uh and i just happen to see a a uh uh
you know i scan actually all
intro psych texts that come across my
feed i have a feed so
and i just saw psychology for students
you know student-friendly version
and it just opens up it says oh what is
mind uh mind is all these things that
are really cool and then it just says
well you can't see it so we sell a
psychologist to study it study
scientifically behavior right okay so
it's like
it does this whole thing here's mine and
then all of a sudden you don't know what
it is
and then they say because it's science
it has to be behavior
which is basically then saying because
we're in the epistemological
category of a third person view then
then we have to frame it this way
um right and and then they're off and
running is that well actually you'd
really want to stop there and
make sure your problem formation is
really clear make sure you don't start
equivocating on what mind is and what
behavior is and what you can see and
what you can't
and do any of that they just proceeded
yeah so that's
that's to me the [ __ ] show um that is
that is the problem
and that's why we're here doing this
thing to untangle the world not so
exactly so thank you that was good
i like it when you when you get in that
rift mode i really like it um
so i want to return back greg to
descartes because we've largely had
what you might call a negative you know
what the problematic
the critical aspect and i think we've
done a lot to really
at least make it plausible that there is
a really difficult
issue of even formulating the problem in
the first place
let alone which is why i tend to be
skeptical of people who just sort of
here's what consciousness is
um and they do some video on it or
promote some argument
um not that they should be ignored i'm
not promoting censorship but
i think that you know unless this
these this intersect inter
interpenetrating set of problems
is is addressed explicit is explicated
and formulated i think the chances of of
uh making progress on the on tangling
the world not are
are very diminished uh 100 i mean
historical problem formulation
the other thing i become very keen on is
what's the epistemological dynamic
what's the ontological reference and are
you being clear
and if i hear somebody saying oh i saw
the problem of consciousness it's this
thing
and it's like and they don't talk
ontology epistemology or historical
grammar of whatever justification system
you're coming from
then it's going to be almost certainly
equivocating and confusing yeah
and that's what your metaphor which
you've drawn for wittgenstein
of all of these language games
that are not using the same sort of
cultural cognitive grammar
using different epistemological frames
having different ontological commitments
um is making this uh very very difficult
indeed
and so yeah you get and and uh as you
know i've have a video out there about
you know how even the various completing
competing disciplines
all like you know neuroscience studies
the brain and it
uses this method and gathers this kind
of data and then psychology as you just
said doesn't know it claims to be
studying behavior
it uses experimental method but blah
blah blah
and then you got computer science that
no we we we don't
we don't study brain and we don't study
right we don't study behavior we make
machines that do information processing
all the methods are different all the
all the theoretical ontologies are
different
the language games are fundamentally
different so when people and they all
use the word mind and cognition
interchangeably but they're talking
about different things that's right so
we have to be very cognizant of that so
let's go very carefully so i want to go
back
to daycare and try and pick up on
something positive from descartes
amen i want to i want to remind
everybody of our first
uh session greg and i had where we
talked about how there's these two
fundamental problems
concerning consciousness and there's
another place by the way
there's even sort of equivocation or um
negligence in the fact that often these
questions
are brought up independently of each
other sometimes confused with each other
and this is the this is the nature of
the generation problem
uh this is broadly speaking how does
something like
the phenomena of mind emerge or
come to be if i i'll use a less
contentious word
come to be in um the world as it's
described by the scientific worldview
and as i'll remind you one more time
this problem commits you to the
scientific worldview if you really want
to solve it because that's how it's
enmeshed
that doesn't mean you have to leave the
scientific worldview unchallenged
but you can't ignore it or dismiss it
amen
so that's the nature or generation
problem
and then there is the other problem
which is the function problem what is it
that consciousness does
and that's a more pressing problem than
faced by descartes because
you know post freud onward and you know
then chomsky and others
we have come to understand how much of
our intelligent behavior
is carried out by unconscious processes
and therefore
what is the special function that
consciousness is bringing
to our intelligent behavior if any at
all
and of course you know and i know there
are some people who propose
that consciousness has no important
function it's almost a purely
epi-phenomenal
entity now descartes does something very
interesting and i think it's instructive
to us
he he doesn't solve these problems but
what he does is the way he formulates
them might be helpful
he formulates them in a way in which he
tries to address
the function and the nature problems
together
and i would argue that that is actually
a very very good strategy to pursue
so what i want to do with you greg is
take a look at go ahead sorry i was just
did uh you are so much more familiar
with descartes than i am in terms of the
depth of his thought and how
did he use this distinction was he
pretty clear on the function
nature distinction or you're just saying
that his intuition and his model
basically blend yeah but he wasn't this
is the latter
very much the latter okay and in fact
i think the integration was so
intuitively apparent to him
that the distinction is one that i'm
anachronistically imposing on him
perfect okay
just want to be clear about that no of
course excellent question
so let's start with the problematic a
problem that descartes
uh faced and um and and unfold a bit of
the problematic around it
so for reasons which we've already sort
of indicated and i know you're doing
work on it so i'll give you a bit of
space to jive on it
uh but uh descartes had come to the
conclusion
that only human beings had consciousness
uh he made that argument because of
their capacity for speech
interestingly notice he's kept he's
capturing an intuition
that we need addressed this is the
intuition
that we attribute consciousness on the
basis of the complexity and flexibility
of creatures cognitive behavior right so
we actually think that intelligence
is some kind of important marker of
consciousness
even though we now know that a lot of
intelligence is unconscious so that's
why this is problematic
but that intuition is nevertheless the
one we
draw upon when we make our attributions
even today so if you ask people
do you think a cat has consciousness
yeah yeah i think a cat has
consciousness
what about a worm ah
yeah exactly unless you're pan psychos
and we'll come back to pennsylvania
later okay so
now what that means is notice what that
intuition
relies on that intuition relies on
the that the nature of consciousness and
the function of consciousness
are actually intimately related right
because i can only attribute
consciousness to other things in terms
of how they're functioning
very broadly construed and so
that is of course i think a very
important intuition
and i'm going to argue that it should
unless we can get an independent
argument for rejecting that intuition
and given that that is the widespread
method by which everybody does the
attribution of consciousness
i think that intuition should be taken
seriously and that is one argument among
many why the nature and the function
problems should be addressed together
yes okay so descartes goes in with this
problem
he says only human beings have
consciousness and because he's
now redefined the soul as consciousness
and all the problematic reasons we
talked about that
um the catholic church sort of likes
that because there's been a
long-standing
christian doctrine which i think might
be undergoing revision right now
um that only human beings have souls
animals don't have souls they they don't
have an afterlife
so the descartes inherits
a problem that faced the christians and
you can see this uh
in their some of their battles with some
of the pagan fosters well
given that animals don't have souls
maybe for
in the aristotelian framework they do
they just have an animal soul they don't
have
even plants have a vegetative soul
exactly exactly
the soil is something much more
functional but let's say given that
so descartes inherits the problem of yes
but animals clearly
are intelligent like a dog right they
can learn they can be trained they can
solve problems
they navigate through the world they
protect themselves they protect their
young
like they seek out and hunt and find
food like this like trying to get a
machine to do all of that
like it's really really wickedly
difficult we don't have artificial
intelligence
that's at that level now okay so
descartes has this problem of okay
if they don't have souls and
consciousness why are they nevertheless
capable of so much intelligence and see
how he's confronting the front
seat greg it's not like i said it's not
explicit but he's bumping into the
relationship between the nature and the
function right
and by the way now i'm also in my own
frame of psychology which lines up with
your cognitive science
okay what we're doing is we're watching
the complex
functional adaptive behavior of animals
right and then we're saying there's
something that's mediating
that dynamic problem-solving adjustment
system
right yes yes and then that's a that's
some sort of brain
intelligence cognition they don't have
to get done have cognition as a term
conscious something right is at least a
mentalist
assertion so so that's that connection
deep connection
just now we have an external view of the
world i.e a behavioral scientific
and we can just watch what animals do
you know um
so uh maybe before we return to
descartes maybe this is a good time i
know you just mentioned before we
started recording
that you're doing you know you're doing
some review and study of
you know the attribution of
consciousness to animals
and you said there's a lot of stuff
coming out about that right now
so we're the position if that's true
that
that the problem that descartes face is
even more pressing for us because
we are even much more aware and it's
even harder for us to
not attribute consciousness to animals
but maybe i've said too much
no no absolutely in fact now there's a i
think it was 2012
i could find the actual thing there was
a declaration of animal consciousness by
um ethologists and comparative
psychologists and
neuroscientists that were studying this
issue and that says absolutely
there's some forms of consciousness in
the in the animal kingdom 100
or at least you know that's our strong
that's why we need to make sure that
everybody knows that scientifically now
we believe descartes is wrong
there's all sorts of reason to believe
that animals have an experience of
there is something that it is like to be
a bat um to use the nagel term
right and so i'll just make a couple of
interesting points at least in my own
just for reference so in terms of deep
consciousness like when does it really
get started
um there are some people uh jablanka if
i hope i say her name right there
uh and her colleagues uh the evolution
of the sensitive soul
uh she they go back essentially to the
cambrian explosion
uh that's about 550 million years ago
and it's really the emergence of
operant learning okay for them is
is that that is the beginning of uh
experience and pleasure and pain and
moving toward and moving away
okay so that's pretty deep and if you
know 500 million years ago 550 million
years ago
and then other individuals are looking
to see that the shape
or contours or functionality of
consciousness so for example
like how much what we would call
perspectival perceptual awareness
as an entity have um some animals seem
to have a lot of that
how much self almost self-awareness or
proto what i call proto-self-awareness
or extension of intuitive self
elephants seem to have a huge amount of
that kind of consciousness
uh so there are some people that are
then starting to really map different
dimensions
uh corresponding to functional responses
brain imagery then
a whole set of assumptions kind of like
global neuronal workspace kinds of
assumptions that are
operative so it's it's really exciting i
think some of the work
thank you that is very cool so let's
let's pick up on the first one
because i think it's a theme running
throughout that the attribution of
consciousness
seems to be paired with the attribution
of intelligence because when you're
getting operant learning
and some capacity for learning and
problems it's very so just for people
are clear so classical learning
is like what a little reflex system will
do and it could become
habituated or sensitized to certain
kinds of stimuli
okay operant learning is when you get a
feedback loop on your consequences
yeah okay when you start doing stuff and
then you extract resources
then you draw your attention and
investment in a particular way
that's so much more fluid and dynamic
yeah
okay and also it makes the creature well
more intelligent
well there it is and maybe more
conscious yeah exactly
exactly so uh within the scientific
community as greg has pointed out
there's a consensus
about the attribution saying
consciousness
exists uh in terms of its functionality
so again trying to keep the nature and
the function problem
uh distinct i think is not an intuition
uh or sorry it's not a a strategy we
should follow
i think decart's intuition um is is well
placed
okay so back to descartes and so let's
back to this problem
and which is the problem of
he's facing the problem of
well let's say like dogs and then we
know he thinks dogs don't have
i don't have souls because he he
justifies doing
you know vivisection on them where
they're still alive because
they they don't have consciousness but
he's aware that dogs are highly
intelligent
and so how does he explain his
intelligence well he brings up something
that's very interesting
um and this is this goes to the work of
my colleague at u of t
uh bill seeger in his book on
consciousness and so i recommend people
to take a look at this
uh because descartes has often been uh
we often are given a caricature of
descartes rather than
an in-depth study and seeger takes
descartes seriously and takes what
descartes does seriously
so descartes says and very interesting
he says well
what animals have um and i'll have to
use some modern language because it's
faster than
trying to his archaic language and then
translate it blah blah blah blah
so but basically what descartes says is
well what
animals have is they have sort of brain
states that reliably covari
with things in the environment right
they reliably co-vary
uh so you know if some object comes in
front of them
there's a brain state and whenever that
object is there that brain state and
so they reliably covari and of course we
have a version of this
you know that's very prominent right now
with the whole predictive processing
model okay so well placed
and also one of the one of the sort of
standard presuppositions of most
models of what a representation is and
you've pointed out that psychologists
often don't even talk about what a
representation is
they just presuppose it but in cognitive
science there's a there's a
you know there's this deep question what
the heck is a representation right
and most models are versions of a
co-variation model
that for me to have a representation of
the world is for me to have some state
in here often my whole embodied
for recognition yeah yeah exactly but
let's just say some
some state in me that reliably covaries
right with the environment uh
and and then what descartes says is okay
and what that'll do is that'll allow the
organism the ability to vary its
behavior the co-variations
variation mechanism yeah vary its
behavior
according to environmental conditions
and that will make the organism
behave in a in an intelligent fashion
but
what is the organism not capable of
doing it's not capable of reasoning
so what's going on there so
here i'm gonna help descartes out by
jumping ahead to
uh the correct discussion about
representation so when you look and
this is we can't do another whole series
on mental representation so
i'm just pointing out again how
challenging this is
and people often often use this term in
a highly equivocal fashion
okay but one of the problems that has
been brought up by cummins and others
about the co-variation theory
and it's a standard it's now there's a
consensus that it is a
genuine problem is that
if i have some object
right and discoveries the problem is the
co-variation
covaries with many things many different
possible mental representations
so if i have an apple in front of me
right this thing is covariate
covariating with an apple
it's co-varying with a fruit it's
co-varying with food
it's co-varying with something in my
hand it's covering with an object that i
can throw
right right and those mental
representations
are much more distinct and specific than
the co-variation
right so representation has a
referential specificity
that covariation does not have right and
what that means
is it is irredeemably vague
in terms of its potential semantic
content so while it may be guiding and
then you know quine also
made this famous with the gava guy
problem
there's all kinds of versions of this so
this is a very uh
right pressing issue
and this also i think is an issue that
needs to be taken up i'm discussing with
mark miller in predictive processing
it's like
yes but what is it you're predicting and
what is it that's selecting
because all of these predictions come
true there's an apple there
there's a fruit there there's food there
there's an object that i can throw there
there's the thing that the witch used to
poison uh snow white there right
all of these predictions are coming true
but they're not all the same claim
because they have different semantic
content and this is something that
descartes
sort of gets that's why he ties
consciousness to language because
language gives you the specificity and
i'll
i'll add just a little quick so from the
unified perspective i'll just say
the constraints then to make that is
going to be behavioral investment which
is an
energy expenditure function like what
does this mean to me and what does it
afford
so exactly connection between uh that
this
object has affordances it has stressors
it has an investment relation
and that's going to constrain some of
that and frame it
in relation yes and i'm gonna i'm gonna
argue and i think you're in agreement
with that
that that's where notions of relevance
realization can be importantly brought
to bear
well that's a key ingredient that seems
to be missing
so descartes descartes seems
and it's hard and it's you know i'm
worried of the i'm worried about the
anachronism by us
but you know seeger is also a very
careful reader
what daycare seems to think is that the
job of consciousness
is to pick out to select from the
covariation
which aspect is to be made ready for
reasoning
so the job of consciousness is to
aspectualize it's to pick out the
aspect that is going to be made
ready for reasoning so that we can
evaluate it for the particular truth so
because reasoning cares with truth cares
about truth
right reasoning needs um co-variations
that have been aspectulized
and specified so their semantic content
is specifiable enough that it can be
evaluated
so he has he has this role for
consciousness but consciousness does
is right when you when right the
co-variations
are are something you sort of uh see
through
you aspectualize them yes and and that's
how you
and so consciousness if this is a bit of
a slogan but it's
mnemonically helpful consciousness turns
co-variations
into representation through a process of
aspect realization
that's really powerful and brilliant yes
so i'll come back to what descartes says
about it oh go ahead please
so let's uh so again i'll make another
reference okay so
when i'm looking at this issue i'm
looking at it from the bottom
in the evolutionary history of animal
consciousness yeah yes yes right
and i'm also then looking at sort of
from the top if you want to use that
uh the tree of knowledge helps me
justify that verdict
and angle and then i want to get into
the unique uh
secondary layer of consciousness that is
human yes
and you when i was listening to this one
in the meaning uh crisis i think you
used this term ready for reasoning
a bit or at least in the other times and
man did a light bulb go off okay
because justification systems yes yes
right
says that language and then reason
giving
means that you now have to give an
account okay
and that means that you do at a
self-conscious level not at a
phenomenological perspectival level but
at a self-conscious level there is the
whole problem of
ready for reason so you can justify
right so so it's like
seeing that descartes saw that as the
problem
you know and then saw that as a
mechanism it's sort of like he's missing
the first
part of consciousness right but he's
actually really honing into the second
part of consciousness you know that i
can see and then remember that connects
directly to what freud ends up seeing in
terms of oh there's an animal
consciousness beneath
and this is how the ego is a mental
organ of justification so there's a lot
of intersections
and and i didn't understand descartes
nearly as well as you did so that made
the light bulb go off for me when i
first heard it
now that you say that uh that that makes
me think of something because
uh you know when we did the reason for
reason we were talking about the
inherently
social cultural nature of reason and
your work on the justification system
and then later work
that is converging with your work by
sperver and most gay people like that
about
how reason is ultimately is mostly done
and mostly should be done
in distributed cognition dialogue it's a
it's a dialogical function that emerges
in nature it's it's not a
abstraction function it's a dialogical
function right
so given that descartes has the
self-enclosed
monological model of mind right he can't
right he can't actually he can't
actually get to
the sociocultural level of cognition
right
and he's then dominated by the modern
science which which gives pristine
um place of analytic reasoning and then
he has to
this is this has to be the highest
function analytical reasoning
and he misses the whole social pragmatic
dimension that would have evolved
obviously
uh prior to these higher order
mathematical
and is always needed even when we're
doing the hospital always needed
that comes later um not you know and
obviously really is a psychotechnology
invention essentially of
of cultural evolutionary justification
processes
i agree so i just wanted to bring that
up because it's another way in which
right the individualistic monolithic
self-imposed misses
modernist yeah neoliberal modern is not
to get into that but yes that's
that is one of the corrections as a
transformation from hyper individualism
into a much more uh networked uh
systemic and social
conception okay that's good
so the but the readiness for reasoning
is going to come back when we talk about
like global work space and stuff like
that so
descartes has a and you know and also
you know block and
ties notion of poisonous and access
consciousness
so descartes i think there's a clear
precursor there
but i want to get up on the this issue
of aspectualization because it's like
what
what you know and that's you know is
that really relevant
um well i want to know jump in yes
yes i want to jump into um
you know somebody who has been a pivotal
figure
in recent cognitive science famous
justifiably famous so
this is john cearl the famous creator of
the chinese room argument which is of
course an
important argument about the nature of
mind and right intelligence and meaning
but cyril has another argument that
people aren't as familiar with from his
book the rediscovery of mine which came
out in
1992. um and cyril makes an argument
that's very interesting now give me a
second on this greg because
as soon as i unfold it you'll then see
how the descartes stuff we just talked
about
is relevant so
cyril goes in and does something that
you and i mentioned needed to be done he
goes in and says he says
wait wait wait wait you're all using
this word representation and mental
representation let's slow down and look
at this okay let's slow down and look at
this
and he he draws on something again and
there's already a long heritage coming
from descartes forward on this at least
have it implicit but often explicit in
many people's work
is that which is the idea and this is
his term in fact
that representations are inherently
aspectual
what does he mean by that he means like
you know
that whenever i'm representing something
and you can you can see how descartes
is like lurking behind you i don't know
if you read this part of descartes or
not
because seeger's work comes later i
think in publication day
but this object has just a huge
number of properties and there's a huge
number of aspects to it unlimited
you know all right and so whenever
and whenever that emerges folks just if
you're playing that means that we have a
combinatorial explosion problem
yes exactly okay which means now you
have a frame problem
that you're not going to be able to
solve unless you put constraints on it
at some level
exactly exactly thank you greg well said
and we'll come back to that again
right i just want to make sure no no i
think that's proper seating for the
whole relevance realization stuff
and the and the and the investment and
your investment theory
okay so what uh what cyril argues is
you know if i represent this as a phone
or as a rectangle
or as a projectile or is the thing given
to me
on my birthday right again we see the
similarity to descartes right
so there's all this has an innumerable
number of features that co-vary with me
right um and so
what cyril says is any representation is
inherently aspectual because out of
all of the properties i select some
subset
and they're not just legally pigelty
they're they're selected as
belonging together as forming
what you know you know the work of
murphy and medine showed that
there's a structural functional
organization with any con within any
concept we have of the thing
right we'll come back to that when we
talk about optimal grip and stuff okay
so i select all out of all the
properties i select some
right in terms of um the ones that are
relevant
yep then i determine how they're
relevant to each other and then also and
this goes back to and this is something
now emphasized by 4e cognition
how it's relevant to me yes oh it's
particularly relevant to me brilliant
brilliant so uh the uh gestalt
psychologists
uh okay this is you know which really
precursors some perceptual cognitive
uh ways of thinking this is a lot of
what they're doing in many ways they're
seeing
laws that pull things together yeah
exactly
in a particular way that force a
particular kind of
uh and if you guys if folks want to you
know get a real experience of this
go check out like a uh a perceptual
illusion like the duck rabbit
depending on how you look at it okay you
will see aspects just in your own
phenomenology they'll jump into a duck
collection and then they'll flip over
and they'll jump into a rabbit
collection
and you'll see the connection of all the
how the aspects actually yeah they don't
they don't randomly co-vary it depend on
what
you're deciding is relevant or what your
frame of
investment is in your relation to it and
all of a sudden it jumps
into those categories and wittgenstein
famously talked about the duck rabbit
and he also invoked the
the term the dawning of an aspect um and
that's
brilliant i didn't know about that yeah
the dawning of an aspect
and you know and the gestalt
psychologist had the famous necker cube
and you've all seen it that
three-dimensional line drawing and
it flips on whether how it's oriented in
three dimensions
so all of this clearly the case and then
so thrills then says okay
so all representations are inherently
aspectual notice how he's already
giving an independent argument
supporting what descartes is doing
that's important but then he does
something really interesting
again which sounds just like descartes
he says ah but every aspect is dependent
on a point of view
right because if i want to see it as a
duck i have this point of view
but if i want to see a as a rabbit i
have this point of view
right if i want to see it as a phone i
have this you know we'll talk about it
later i have this perspectival knowing
of it yep because if i want to see it as
a
a weapon i have this etc etc
and then you go okay that sounds
reasonable point of view yep yep
and then he says aha now i have you
and notice how this sounds like
descartes and i think it's completely
independent but convergent he said
but point of view is dependent on having
consciousness
things can only have a point of view if
there's a viewer
and the metaphor of sight is being used
for to stand for all of
conscious awareness so a point of view
centers on a consciousness and then
cyril makes this argument he says
well you know what that means that means
that
there are no purely
unconscious representations
and he seems to have a view that is
remarkably similar to dakar he seems to
think that the brain has something like
states that could vary
and they only become representations
when they're actually brought
into consciousness and for similar
reasons
that's where they are in a sense made
ready for reason
because they are now given a determinate
content
so descartes that's not just a dusty
argument and then there was a lot of
kerfuffle about this because what
what cyril then said is so all this talk
about unconscious representations that
are in
that can never be brought into
consciousness like chomsky's using or
you know or you know maybe you know even
some of the psychodynamic stuff or any
of the learning theorists
all of that's just no good because those
are those can't be representations
okay so people got like all upset and
everything right right
all of a sudden you got a language
police problem and whatever
but yeah now what i want to say to that
is i think what you've got is an
independent and converging argument
and we've drawn a lot of people together
wittgenstein the gestalt
right right for the the prop that
there's a deep connection
between representation and
aspectualization
and there's a deep connection between
aspectualization and consciousness
this has to be unpacked now cyril and
descartes are making a very linear
right uh representation depends on our
specialization which depends on
consciousness
and that's the function of consciousness
now what i want to argue
is but maybe there's another way of
doing another way of getting that
the order right right what i want to
argue
is that maybe there is something
deeper that is needed
for aspect realization and this is what
we've
alluded to and notice how i invoked it
when i
described how you form a representation
and this is the process
of relevance realization of the
combinatorial explosive
amount of information available to you
in the object
i zero in on what's relevant and then
how those pieces belong and fit together
in a way that's relevant to me this
complex
relevance realization going on right and
so
what if we what if we inverted the order
and said no no
maybe relevance realization can generate
representation
and the aspectualization and maybe
aspectualization then can give rise to
consciousness what if we reverse the
causal error because of course one of
the most
prominent problems that human beings
fall into is the a b confusion of
causation right
right right what if
there is lots of unconscious processing
that's doing relevance realization
that then makes a specialization
possible in representation
and then that aspectualization can be a
basis for
consciousness itself
then we would get out of all the
problems that descartes
and searle are giving us right and that
immediately has
resonance around a wide variety of
different domains yes
i mean uh so
i'll just say one for example okay
so when we think about making something
an aspect that becomes salient um folks
i'm sure of the experience of everything
that you
much of what you do if you do it over
and over again all of a sudden we'll
drift it at least into pretty far away
consciousness
right yes they sort of get into a
procedural way of being that is pretty
far away from
our conscience but then all of a sudden
you get surprised okay
and that consciousness all immediately
comes back online all right
yep exactly exactly so if all of a
sudden then the aspect of that system
needs to be brought together to
integrate a whole brain function to
start to
connect things so that you can then
start engaging mental manipulation and
problem solving
that's beautiful greg and notice how
what the experience of
insight does for you the insight
like you know remember when you talk
about how the duck rabbit flips well you
get that same kind of flip in an insight
you've been framing it one way and it
reframes another way
and notice how that is accompanied and
it's prototypically even
with the icon of the light bulb there's
a flash there's a
right right and there's uh there's a
there's a somehow there's an
accentuation of consciousness
in that salience restructuring of what
we find relevant your perspective
opens up yes yes and see if we if we
invert the order of explanation
by inverting the order of causation we
can start to explain
all of these phenomena and we can also
explain how a lot of your unconscious
behavior
could nevertheless be so sophisticated
um
in terms of its intelligence amen so
i want to propose to you that there's
now that means uh that brings up two
competing
vehicles for consciousness right one is
that consciousness is a function
of representational content
and that and of course the problem there
is well we have so many unconscious
representation
right right let's say we and so what
many people do
they reject cyril is what they do is
they say well consciousness is some kind
of
representation some kind of meta
representation it's representations of
representations
because this they know in consciousness
the mind somehow touches
itself and we'll take a look at that and
there's
there's i mean that's a that's that's an
intelligent proposal but it's
problematic
i want to propose to you and this is
perhaps where i'm being
perhaps innovative um that instead of
trying to build consciousness out of
representational content
we try to build it out of the process of
aspectualization
that is presupposed by representation
right
and also presupposed by consciousness
and i want to argue that we could
explain that aspectualization
in terms of processes that are neither
themselves intelligent or consciousness
but neither intelligent nor conscious
namely the process of relevance
realization
right that's setting up that argument
there right and
and that's i believe certainly anything
i've seen
i'll say uh talk about a light bulb when
i heard you first
lay this out you know i was excited all
day okay
so i i think it's a hell of a i think
it's a hell of an innovation and
certainly if
it all i mean i got i i wrote you or
whatever i was you know so yeah
it's it's as we're teasing it a little
bit here but it's like yeah no this is a
big
shift certainly for me and i thought
quite a fair amount about these issues
so
well that's why i'm in dialogue with you
i think you've thought of a fair amount
and you thought very well
um so
what i'm pointing to is that realization
might give us sorry
might be the basis for an integrated
response
as to what consciousness does it
aspectulizes
so that there are representations and it
does further aspectualization
so that those representations are ready
for reason right all that
and we're going to come back to that and
we might see that in the shift as you
already indicated from
things being relevant to us the things
being salient to us
we'll talk about that we'll talk about
that in a minute right
and then that might also help to explain
the
nature or the emergence of consciousness
because if you can get a system that is
capable of relevance realization
then it can start to aspectulize and
then it can start to get
the basis of what we're going to talk
about when we talk about perspective
we'll know it yeah
so we might be able to go ahead let me
add that uh
so we talked about uh you know making
ready for reason
okay um but actually what i'm gonna then
suggest is really when we're talking
about the evolution it's gonna be ready
for simulation
yes yes okay so then in other words so a
rat can get to a maze and then simulate
which side of the team is that they're
gonna go to okay
and then they're gonna they'll run
through particular uh investment paths
and make some cost-benefit calculation
around that
so this goes towards a theory one of the
neuroscientific theories we're going to
invest
the information closer theory that
argues that the main function
of consciousness is to afford
counter-factuality
that we can uh right we can
organisms can work in a hypothetical
space
uh which of course is not the same thing
as cold lawn reason
but it is again deeply presupposed by
all reasoning
it sets the stage for it very much
nice metaphor there okay so let's talk a
little bit about
this aspectualization and i want to move
to some
work and sort of build up to it a little
bit more i want to work
move to the work of zen and pollution
um which he's got i think the most
science fiction sounding name of anybody
in cognitive science
his last name by the way everybody does
not have any vowels in it it's all it's
all what it's all the letter y coalition
um and so and we have to understand
where pollution is coming from pollution
is one of the godfathers with jerry
fodor
of computational functionalism and the
computational theory of mind
so the fact that he's going to make the
argument that he makes
is is something that he was led to
by the data being generated in his
experiments because it
it significantly challenges in some ways
the standard model
that he had developed with voter about a
computational theory of mind at least
to many people's minded to my mind so
what pollution was doing was he was
actually
studying vision and what you might even
call visual attention
and we're going to have to get into what
a relationship we're doing attention
awareness and consciousness which is
brat
so just give me for those of you who are
already getting your knives out just
wait
wait okay give me a chance uh but what
he was doing is he's doing a thing
called multiple object tracking so let's
say there's a computer screen
and there'll be a bunch of shapes on it
like a bunch of x's and zeros
and then they're moving around and let's
say the x's are all different colored
like red and green
what you have to do is you have to track
them so let's say there's a green
x and it starts here and you have to be
able to tell me where it ends and here's
you know a pink circle here where does
it end now you may think well i can only
do one object at a time it turns out no
you can't
you can do more than that and uh you can
there's some question about how big this
is between five and eight let's say
controversy you can track that's why
it's called multiple
object tracking yeah okay you say well
who cares about this well just hang on a
sec
okay uh so
what what politician uh noticed
is as you max out how many things
are trapped there's a trade-off
relationship and that's gonna
trade-off relationships are gonna be key
to relevance realization there's a
trade-off relationship
between how many objects you can track
and how many properties you can
attribute to each object
so as i open up the number of objects
i'm tracking and i sort of
overload this system with demand what
happens is
that people
well let me describe it in terms of what
happens in the experiment
so let's say there's this thing here on
the computer screen and it started as
a is a red circle and while it's moving
it changes into a green
x it changes its color and its shape
people don't notice the change in color
and shape
right all they can all they can say is
whatever started there
is now there there okay so
they don't they they lose any
um conceptual properties for the object
all they have
is what uh politician called fingers of
instantiation and then he
created this instinct and the idea is
this
like if i like he thought of like the
mind has like like
like almost like elastic fingers but it
doesn't know what this is but it can
put its finger on it and know where it
goes
where it is where it is right like this
right right let me use an example so
that
uh so remember we were just talking
about the duck rabbit thing right right
right to maintain attention on it then
all the aspect realization comes there
but you can then basically zoom out just
have an outline of that thing
okay and have some notion about its
positionality
but you'll lose your contact with the
tax with the
richness right exactly so all of the
uh all of the sort of adjectival content
disappears now what's left
is and if you have to forgive me people
but i'm gonna
need to talk this way and the fact that
we don't have ready available terms
has actually been part of the language
game problem
but what is this doing well it's it's
here now
here now here now here now here now here
now here now
so this is called invexicality
indexicals are things
that don't have a categorical
content to them let me so here's an
indexical
this okay i can use this for anything
this this this this
right that's different from cat
cat has a content to it yes like a set
of properties
okay right so this is a purely indexical
tracking here now here now here now
here now so i'm going to call this
these are adverbial qualias
they are not adjectival quality as like
shape
or color or kind of thing it is
right they are merely adverbial they are
telling you
right where and when here now here now
and all they're doing all they're doing
is what i call salience tagging
when your finger touches this it's
making this here now this
salient to you yep standing out for you
that's all it is it's salient tagging
there's no adjectival content to it it's
purely
adverbial it's pure here now
now you might say okay who cares ah then
politician has this really powerful
argument i'm just gonna
get another object here and another one
here
i should have done this ahead of time no
uh but uh it's it's important yeah
okay so politian
requests from us that we understand he's
going to use a metaphor
he's going to use a metaphor from
language but he does not need to imply
that the process he's describing
is a linguistic process right it is a
linguistic metaphor
for a much more primordial process
because
he thinks i think correctly and there's
evidence for it that animals have to be
able to do even
this object tracking right thing okay so
what's the linguistic metaphor
i just used that a few minutes ago the
linguistic metaphor is the linguistic
metaphor of demonstrative reference
so things have categorical reference
words like cat
dog right chicken right
but there are things that only have
demonstrative reference because they're
purely indexical
i can only do the reference in
demonstration like when i say
this it this yes
so all i'm doing is here now this
is being salient to you this
salience tagging yep demonstrative
reference now
collision says notice that you need
demonstrative reference in order to form
your categories he says
if i'm going to form a category i have
to mentally
draw things together i have to go this
this
this i have to first i have to have a
pre-categorical ability to draw them
make them salient together in the same
here now-ness
so fencing salience tagging
is actually presupposed
by any categorical identity right
so before i can aspectualize this
as a pencil yep i have to have first
had something that allowed me to draw
things together adverbially
because there's no adjectival content
because there's no category
i don't know there's no wetness to this
is i just have it's
this this this ah now that they're drawn
together and salient
they're right they're right together in
the same here and this nowadays
now i can start to see how they belong
together
and i can start to categorize them and
find patterns of similarity and draw out
particular aspects
[Music]
so that means what pollution argues
what he's uncovering in the multiple
object tracking
is something that is deeper he says it's
presupposed
by all of our conceptual abilities and
here's notice what it's doing it's
making things ready for reason
by drawing them together through
salience tagging
so that similarity can be noticed
between them and similarity we'll argue
later is it
just an inherently a relevance
realization function i see how they
belong together
right and that makes aspect realization
possible
it's brilliant as far as i'm concerned i
mean
let me i'll riff off this real uh see
where why i had such a positive reaction
to this
okay from my own journey and sort of
some sense-making stuff that i was doing
um so you know i'm really big on
concepts of behavior figuring out what
that is
yeah of course at multiple levels uh
like one of the things is what is the
relationship between phenomenology and
behavior
both epistemologically and they're
really
very fascinating uh ontological
relations across multiple levels
okay so for example our capacity to pull
objects all right and then track their
changes
yes all right yeah uh and i became you
know convinced by a whole host of
different
uh data um but i'll get to the language
issue in just a second
that that's that what is happening um is
that we have perceptual categorical
fields
for objects in fields okay yeah
and how they change and then what are
their constituent
elements that make them up okay um
and so now let's run to make another
connection here in the human mind and
the formation of language
okay um so what are the what are the
fundamental
elements of of grammar and language and
syntax
okay the fundamental categories of is a
noun
yes all right okay so that's the thing
okay a verb which is how the thing
changes right and then adjectives
which are corresponding to differences
in
within the noun or okay so i was like
yeah okay so there's a very clear
symbolic tag noun verb adjective right
yeah but what i overlooked and what this
brought to bear is well yeah and that
presupposes
the existence of a categorical system
that's defining objects
right right and changes that sets the
stage for them to be honed in on if need
be but you need to have that frame
right i never really had brought i was
seeing through the lens of the frame
but your system then immediately caused
me to jump out and say oh right the
frame has got to be built
yes exactly frame has got to be built to
presuppose all of this
so i was like oh i i hadn't really had
that
piece of awareness and then when you do
it and it lines up the way and then you
could say well wait a minute
the presupposing of that frame the
machinery the functionality
uh all that that starts to line up with
a lot of cool things
that's well said thank you greg and what
pollution argument is showing and what
i think i have conversion arguments for
pick up on this language you're using
is any of the processes within the
framing
right are not going to be processes that
are going to you're going to be able to
use to explain how the frame is
generated in the first place
because you're just if all the processes
within the framing presuppose the
framing
and therefore are not going to be able
to explain it and that's exactly
what collision is saying he's saying all
of the conceptual machinery
right and all of the i would argue the
representational machinery
is not going to be able to explain this
because
right it is based on a process that is
presupposed
by this least in the sense of
pre-categorical preconceptual
machinery of fencing of salience tagging
absolutely i'm reminded of the
experiments i'm blanking exactly on
there's a whole cluster of them sure you
are aware mostly social psych
experiments uh like where a guy
is talking to somebody they don't know
that well yeah yeah yeah yeah changing
and
something yeah there it is of course
yeah thank you for that yep
change mine that's right so yeah people
will yeah you can do a thing where
you're talking to somebody
a bunch of people walk past it's a
stranger right
with like a like they're just excuse me
and they pass like
they care a piece of plywood and while
they're passing that person
is replaced by another person sometimes
different gender even
right race can change very yeah people
don't notice that it's a different
person
right right and whenever you say that
everybody in the everybody out there
right now is saying oh i've noticed
yeah right right whatever like like the
gorilla experiment yeah
i'd see it well actually
now it's amazing but that just shows how
much operation
maybe is going on with basic fenstein
which we assume
is doing aspect realization but it's
actually oh my god how much
you know cognitive work is being done by
just organizing where things are
and then you know filling in the blind
spots when we need to but a lot of it is
just
running off of you know that frame
thank you okay so let's do a quick cycle
back to descartes and then we'll look
so notice what i'm doing i'm swinging
between descartes and current you know
important cognitive scientists like
searle and politician right and notice
we've got both conceptual arguments from
cyril and experimental data
uh from pollution both you know you know
the argument is
in a good argument it should be taken
seriously and the data is robust and
reliable
replicate it replicates well et cetera
et cetera all that stuff
okay so descartes let's go back what
does descartes think's going on
well he isn't in it and he's struggling
and there's vagueness there
but um again through the through uh
you know from the help of bill seeger by
the way i'm not claiming that bill
seeger and i
bill seeger agrees with everything i say
but i'm giving due credit
for his important uh uh affording
influence on me
so they people know some of this story
descartes has the famous idea about the
pineal gland
right and you know enough that's no
solution to the problem
but putting aside that it fails to solve
the mind brain problem
you should notice what descartes is
doing he seems to think that all of
these co-variations somehow get super
imposed on each other and somehow
integrated
into consciousness all right
and that's part of how this aspect
realization takes place
so he uses the metaphor of you know
super super imposition right
um that somehow brings an integration
but when i when i read that i thought oh
crap there's two different people from
two different traditions
that i think are talking about that um
one is michael palani
okay coming out of sort of you know the
analytic
uh north american scientific tradition
he's originally a scientist then he
becomes a philosopher
um and then there's martial ponty french
person
french person coming out of the
phenomenological tradition right
so i normally do this with people about
uh
like uh actually run through it but i'll
just describe and i and i've done this
multiple times and that's why these
examples are used by poland
and used by marlo ponte and used
repeatedly and convert and they were
independent of each other
as far as i can tell uh marlo ponti
doesn't know anything about planning i
don't think pelani knows marvel pontiac
at all
let me just describe i'm going to use
touch because touch is slower
than sight um and then therefore you can
have sort of more introspective
awareness of what i'm talking about
so what i do is i'll often you know you
know hold up your hand and i'm going to
put an object in your hand
i know what this object is but pretend
you don't and right
or i'll put it on the table in front of
you and you're going to close your eyes
as if you're a blind person and you're
going to tap it
with right an object this is going to be
your probe
this is the blind man's cane uh again
used
independently by both pilani and marla
ponti
and so and what you're going to do is
you're going to tap it
and you're tapping it to aspectualize it
you're tapping it so that
you can right from the tappings you'll
be able to and notice this is a weird
thing figure out
what it is right and of course you're
going to figure it out according
that's the aspect of it but notice what
notice what i'm getting
i'm getting i'm getting a moment of
instinct here now
here now here now here now here now here
now is that is that okay
yeah salience tagging but when people do
this
right they'll often they can often tell
me oh yeah yeah yeah yeah i get it it's
a phone it's a phone
right and then i'll say okay keep
tapping it but now instead of
paying attention to what it is pay
attention to what your pencil is doing
how it's making those moments of contact
and they go yeah i can do that
i say can you now also instead of paying
attention to your pencil pay attention
to how your fingers are moving the pet
oh yeah
and then i'll say now see if you can pay
attention to the sensations by which
you're feeling your fingers
and some people can and some people can
interestingly this is only anecdotally i
haven't done this experimentally but
it's
very reliable the people who can who can
become aware of the sensations in their
finger
are often people who've had mindfulness
training
okay and then and then i say and then
you can go to reverse you can go from
okay stop paying attention to your
sensations in your fingers
right pay attention to your pencil and
then stop paying attention to your
pencil stop
start paying attention again to the
phone yep
so notice what's happening right there's
all these
layers in there so i use a metaphor here
uh and it's a metaphor used by actor
a psychologist met singer a philosopher
so again convergence and so this is the
metaphor
it's a transparency opacity shift let me
use
give you the analogy and you use the
metaphor so right now
i'm and notice that notice how they're
also framing
right i'm looking through my glasses
which means
i'm looking by means of them and beyond
them both
by means of them beyond them so they are
transparent to me
i don't see them i see through them
i'm not aware of them i'm aware through
them
but i can do this oh
now i'm not aware i'm not skiing through
my glasses
i'm not looking through them i'm looking
at them they're opaque to me
because i'm looking at them i'm not
looking through them i can step back and
look out
in a similar way initially i'm not
if you'll allow me to use looking as a
metaphor here right
not looking at my pencil i'm looking
through my pencil at the object
but i can step back and look at the
pencil
right now what am i looking through i'm
looking through my fingers at the pencil
and then i can step back and look at my
fingers
right and then i can even some people
they've had the training the practice
i can step back and look at my
sensations and i can go the other way
so each time i step back and look at i'm
doing a transparency opacity shift
and each time when i go the other way
i'm doing an opacity to transparency
shift
and what's happening is things
moments of salience tagging and that's
maybe what sensations maybe
primitively are are being integrated
into an aspect
and then those and then those aspects
are integrated into further aspects
and so on and so forth and and so
planning talked about
that attention has a from two structure
i'm always attending through what he
calls
my subsidiary awareness into my focal
awareness
i'm attending through my pencil yep
to the phone so i use this example when
i came
across it okay and then i was like oh my
god looking through looking at
and i was loving that all right i was on
on my walk and i was like oh my god i
could
i could now see this i was really
excited and then actually it evolved
okay so one of my arguments about the
evolved into a real useful tool that i
think at least other people have now
told me oh i get what you're saying
okay so one of my key points uh in my
critique of psychology science
is work enormous ambiguity about the
concept of behavior
right right right okay um and actually
my argument is that one of the
huge problems with it is that it has
three different meanings
okay one of which is epistemological
yes right based on you step outside and
then you look at the object field change
which modern science forced us to make
that shift which we then quantify
in relationship to primary entities
right
right right okay and so now basically
that requires
then a grammar from an exterior to use
ken wilbur's term an exterior
epistemology
right right right and then that frames
either everything that's why like
physics some physicists describe physics
as the behavior
it's the science of the behavior of the
universe at all scales
that's what physicists will sometimes
say okay so that's a general definition
that's not then if psychology
can't be the science of behavior yeah
okay
yeah okay if physics is the science of
behavior at all scales
i mean if atoms behave then we can then
psychology can't be the science of
behavior
it has to be a science of a behavior of
a particular kind
yes right okay and that's what i argue
actually the class
of behaviors using the tree of knowledge
taxonomy should be
mental behaviors right right right right
both overt that you see directly and
covert that you infer
revelation okay so so then in my book
i'm saying hey
scientists stop looking through
the frame of behavior take the behavior
glasses off
right and see that actually the grammar
of your justification system is
essentially framed by looking through
the behavioral glasses and if we become
aware of that then we can become aware
of the language game that science
plays uh and the grammar that they
structured it around
and i structured around i'm a scientist
but we want to be aware
of the rules and and framing uh that
really drive the system
no that was beautiful greg that's really
good
so i want to come back to that actually
at some point because
notice how your metacognitive ability is
making use of the transparency opacity
shifted
and how it's presupposed in our ability
to
make ourselves ready for reason namely
do some kind of self-correction in our
problem solving
well you gave me one of the many light
bulbs you gave me john as i listened to
your work
thank you for saying that well you're
sharing it back fred
um so notice what we have here
we have we have some we have a process
that
helena calls integration you have to be
a little bit careful of that word though
and he is careful he's not equivocating
because there's two senses of
integration there's integration in which
you know you know here's the parts of a
chair and they're integrated together
you can still
see all the parts right but what he's
talking about is more like
this i have like i have a left field of
vision
and a right field of vision and you can
you can do this put your finger
and open and close your eye and you can
see your finger move right
you and what your brain does is it i
would say it fuses them like like
like like atomic fusion but it's that
kind of it's the kind of integration in
which the
left and right visual field you don't
see the left and right visual field you
see
through them into depth perception i
don't
right i don't see the moments of tapping
i see through them
to do the object so i am doing some kind
of
like fusion integration of
salience tappings of moments of hear
nowness
and that is actually a process by which
i am aspectualizing them bringing them
into a kind of focal awareness
which is a higher form of salience out
of all the things that initially
are like grabbing my attention this is
now given extra attention
and at the same time i'm aspectualizing
something
i'm right i'm integrating those things
in a particular
right into a particular structural
functional organization so
again descartes seems to have been
intuitively on the right track
there's some sense in which i have all
these co-variations
moments of co-variation and then when
they are integrated in this way
and i'm going to argue that that's kind
of a data compression thing happening in
relevance realization
later but when they're integrated i get
the aspect realization
i'm now ready for reason both in the
sense that i've
begun the process of giving it
categorical content and also your point
i've now made it metacognitively
available for self-correction
two of the things presupposed in making
something ready for reason
right and then you can see that part of
what
consciousness is doing then is and maybe
i would argue the pivotal thing that
consciousness is doing
is this process of recursive relevance
realization that is
making aspectualization possible for us
right and i want to and so for me then
what i want to say is
when i hear that i'm like oh okay
yeah and and the reason that this is
another light bulb are all tangled
together in this particular kind of
light bulb is notice folks
what we're doing now or what john is
doing and then i'm really uh
latching on to is we're really building
this
cognitive functional view of what
consciousness is about this witnessing
function of framing and
spectralizing yeah right okay we have
not talked
about what does almost everybody talk
about in consciousness oh redness
how the heck does redness happen okay
that's certainly where i
you know go and it is an important part
of this uh equation undoubtedly
but notice we haven't talked about the
the features and the experiential
qualia we have talked about framing
um and the functionality of framing that
sets the stage for aspectualization
okay so that to me is that's like oh
this is a
that's what feels so huh and then when
we see that relation as it will come
back
it's going to be really really important
so for me that was a
really cool oh wow it's like a common at
this uh with a very rich
view from a different angle than i yeah
thank you for saying that i mean so yeah
this is very much
building consciousness at least the
functionality and maybe some of the
phenomenology
of consciousness out of the adverbial
qualia first
right and really getting going as far as
we can with them
before we turn to the problematic
adjectival qualia like redness and
blueness
right right so so it's the thing that's
framing
object fields the structure of object
fields without getting in
to the quality qualities of those object
fields we have to have a
we have to have a way to bring hereness
and and nowness to the object field
framing relation right and then there's
a third thing there's the hereness
the nowness and with the integration the
togetherness yes
the hereness the now-ness and the
togetherness and this goes to what uh
uh marlo ponte called optimal gripping
um and this is the idea that
you're always and and and and mason in
his book sentience talked about this in
terms of what he called sizing up
so whenever i'm specializing i'm sizing
up in order to get an optimal grip
because
right so like do i look do i look at the
object here well i might if i need the
details
do i look at the object there well you
know that's pretty good
too uh for the gestalt but i've lost
some of the deep
so typically i'll try and find a place
where i get and they're in a trade-off
relationship
right so i'm going to get the place
where i get sort of the optimal balance
between the the the features and the
gestalt
but what counts as an optimal balance is
again
well what's relevant to me and the task
that i'm undertaking
if i want to throw this at you i'm going
to optimally grip it in a different way
if i want to write with it
or if i want to paint it right
so that aspectualization is also
simultaneously a process of sizing up
what that means is i'm getting
trade-offs between what's foregrounded
and backgrounded
what is gestalt and what is feature
and and all of that is relative to what
what
what problems or tasks am i undertaking
and of course this is part of your
whole point about uh you're making
decisions about how am i investing
right how am i investing my metabolic
energy my precious
all the way all the way down the
bioenergetic scale right so you're
you're a vector uh moving toward and
away things
so yeah that frames that but yes that's
absolutely right so the promise i'm
going to leave people with because i
think we should end it here is
that all of that stuff we're talking
about right about the trading off and
investing the bioeconomic
and and doing all of this
zeroing in on relevance that's going to
be i'm going to discuss that with greg
explicitly when we move to the topic and
the theory of relevance realization
but that's where i think we can leave it
for today i think we've made some
important progress today absolutely and
so i'll just just summarize okay so a
fundamental shift here folks
greg you're we're really quiet all of a
sudden um
i'll summarize a fun is that better a
little bit better yeah
i'll summarize just a fundamental point
the shift between
uh adjectival qualia into adverbial
qualia
and the framing of what we are doing to
bring that hereness nowness togetherness
uh is absolutely a fundamental shift in
my opinion
that really opens up so many different
uh novel insights
i agree well a great journey again
together
today my friends so thank you very much
that was really good and thank you for
that summary
and we will pick this up and we'll move
forward and we're gonna we'll take a
look at meta representational theories
of uh of consciousness and then we're
gonna move properly into
uh you know neuroscientific theories of
consciousness
great great fantastic alrighty okay i'll
see you soon my friend take good care